A Guide to Dr. Vamik D. Volkan Papers
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Dr. Vamik D. Volkan Papers 1929-2004
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
VDA
The collection consists of 1650 items in 35 Hollinger boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5", 14.5 linear feet, of processed materials.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Dr. Vamik Volkan donated his papers to the University of Virginia Health Sciences Library starting in 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Vamik D. Volkan (born 1932 in Cyprus) is an emeritus professor of Psychiatry at the University of Virginia. He is also the Senior Erik Scholar at the Austen Riggs Center in Stockbridge, Massachusetts, an emeritus training and supervising analyst at the Washington Psychoanalytic Institute, Washington, D.C., and a past president of both the International Society of Political Psychology (ISPP) and the Virginia Psychoanalytic Society. In 1987, he founded the Center for the Study of Mind and Human Interaction (CSMHI) at the University of Virginia School of Medicine and directed the Center until 2002. Throughout the 1990s he served as a member of the Carter Center's International Negotiation Network, headed by former President Jimmy Carter. Currently, he is the president of the American College of Psychoanalysts (ACOPSA), (2009-2010).
For 30 years, Dr. Volkan has been dedicated to carrying out projects in various troubled spots in the world, especially in the Middle East and the former Soviet Union including Greece, Turkey, Estonia, Georgia and Kuwait. He endeavored to bring together ethnic groups in conflict for dialogue while developing new psychopolitical theories about large-group behavior in times of peace and war. Currently, Dr. Volkan is involved in the Islamic-Western Dialogue and PAKH project (Psychotherapeutical Working Group for Persons Affected by the Holocaust). Dr. Volkan published more than 50 books and 400 scientific papers and book chapters, and his work has been translated into many languages. Dr. Volkan was nominated for the Nobel Peace Prize in 2005, 2006, 2007, and 2008.
Scope and Content Information
This Collection is divided into his major projects including the Turkish-Greek project, the Estonian project, the Kuwait project, the Georgia project, the Islamic- Western Dialogue, PAKH (Psychotherapeutical Working Group for Persons Affected by the Holocaust) project, the Carter Center project, the Chautauqua project, and CSMHI (Center for the Study of Mind and Human Interaction). The collection also includes his papers, review articles of his books and papers, newspaper articles, correspondence, information about meetings and conferences he attended, and recommendation letters for the Nobel Peace Prize.
Contents List
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Volkan's Application for Membership to the American Psychoanalytic Association, January, 1973, TD (Box-folder 001:001)
  Application Form
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Confirmation of Annual Salary for Volkan, Director of the Blue Ridge Hospital, October 4, 1980, TD (Box-folder 001:002)
  Letter
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Who's Who from the Virginia Medical(March, 1982, Vol.109), March of 1982, TD (Box-folder 001:003)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Biography of Vamik D. Volkan(from the Middle East Institute), 1988, TD (Box-folder 001:004)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: The American College of Psychoanalysists, 1989, TD, Photo(1) (Box-folder 001:005)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Boyer Prize Winning for Best Article in Psychoanalytic Anthropology, 1997(January), TD (Box-folder 001:006)
  Letters
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Interview with Vamik Volkan "It is Still Too Early For the Dialogue Between Croats and Serbs. They Need Some Time to Mourn Thier Losses, 1997-1998, TD (Box-folder 001:007)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Wolf Werdigier's Portfolio: Hidden Images, 2003, Portfolio Pamphlet (Box-folder 001:008)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Mutual Educational Exchange Grant From the Fulbright/Sigmund-Freud-Society, 2005(March 22), TD (Box-folder 001:009)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Dr. Vomik D. Volkan's CV, 2008(April), TD (Box-folder 001:010)
- Vamik D.Volkan CV: Author Biography from Barnes & Noble, ND, TD (Box-folder 001:011)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Sleep - A Biographical Study", 1962, 1962 (Box-folder 001:012)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Five Poems by Negro Younsters Who Faced a Sudden Desegregation", 1963, TD (Box-folder 001:013)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Observation and Topographic Study of the Changing Ego States of a Schizophrenic Patient", 1964, TD (Box-folder 001:014)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Observation of the 'Little Man' Phenomenon in a Case of Anorexia Nervosa", 1965, TD (Box-folder 001:015)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Some Observations of the Psychodynamic Processes", 1966(11), TD (Box-folder 001:016)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Normal and Pathological Grief Relations", 1966(11), TD (Box-folder 001:017)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Some Considerations of Satellite States and Satellite Dreams", 1968, TD (Box-folder 001:018)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Known Object Loss, Disturbance in Reality Testing, and "Re-Grief Work" as a Method of Bried Psychotherapy", 1968, TD (Box-folder 001:019)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Introjection of Identification with the Therapist As An Ego-Building Aspect in the Treatment of Schizophrenia", 1968, TD (Box-folder 001:020)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Descriptive Study of a Psychiatric Word in a General University Hospital", 1969(8), TD (Box-folder 001:021)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: Studies on mourning process (UVa research) in Turkish medical world monthly journal 1969(11), TD (Box-folder 001:022)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Typical Findings in Pathological Grief", 1970, TD (Box-folder 001:023)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "An Experiment in the Initial Phase of Education for the Psychiatrist", 1970, TD (Box-folder 001:024)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Emotional Flooding and Related Emotional States", 1970(5), TD (Box-folder 001:025)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Theory and Practice of Psychiatry in Turkey", 1971, TD (Box-folder 001:026)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Study of a Patient's "Re-Grief Work" Through Dreams, Psychological Tests and Psychoanalysis", 1971, TD (Box-folder 001:027)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The 'Fieldwork' Method of Teaching and Learning in Clinical Psychiatry", 1971, TD (Box-folder 001:028)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Aspects of the Object Relationships and Developing Skills of a 'Melancholy Boy'", 1971, TD (Box-folder 001:029)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Learning Group", 1972(3), TD (Box-folder 001:030)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Recognition and Prevention of Pathological Grief", 1972(5), TD (Box-folder 001:031)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychiatry in Pre-Baccalaureate Education", 1972(5), TD (Box-folder 001:032)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Birds of Cyprus", 1972(7), TD (Box-folder 001:033)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "the Linking Objects of Pathological Mourners", 1972(8), TD (Box-folder 001:034)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transitional Fantasies in the Analysis of a Narcissistic Personality", 1972(9), TD (Box-folder 001:035)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Dreams of Transsexuals Awaiting Surgery", 1973(5), TD (Box-folder 001:036)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Death, Divorce and the Physician", 1974, TD (Box-folder 001:037)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Cauthionary Psychiatric Insight", 1974, TD (Box-folder 001:038)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Food, Body Shape and Sexuality", 1974, TD (Box-folder 001:039)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Transsexual Issue", 1974, TD (Box-folder 001:040)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Turkey", 1975, TD (Box-folder 001:041)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Re-Grief Theory and the Function of the Linking Object As a Key to Stimulate Emotionality", 1975, TD (Box-folder 001:042)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Review: Adasal's Book, [Normal and Abnormal Sexuality and Marriage], 1975, TD (Box-folder 001:043)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "More on 'Re-Grief' Theory", 1975, TD (Box-folder 001:044)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Cosmic Laughter: A Study of Primitive Splitting", 1975, TD (Box-folder 002:001)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: 1975(3), TD (Box-folder 002:002)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: 1975(5), TD (Box-folder 002:003)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: 1975(7), TD (Box-folder 002:004)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Task Force of Psychiatry and Foreign Affairs", 1975(12), TD (Box-folder 002:005)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Schizophrenia: Primitive Object Relationships in Treatment", 1976, TD (Box-folder 002:006)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Review: R. Kayar's Book, [Concepts of Health and Disease and the "View" of Medicine in Present Day Society], 1976, TD (Box-folder 002:007)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychiatric Aspects of Surgical Treatment for Problems of Sexual Identification", 1976, TD (Box-folder 002:008)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Grief Over Death: Its Complications", 1976, TD (Box-folder 002:009)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychiatric Problems with the Satellite-Extended Families of Turkey", 1976(7), TD (Box-folder 002:010)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Mourning and Adaptation After a War", 1977, TD (Box-folder 002:011)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Immortal Ataturk: Narcissism and Creativity in a Revolutionary Leader", 1977, TD (Box-folder 002:012)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Adolescents in the In-patient Service: Questions about Their Treatment," in Turkish medical world monthly journal 1977(5), TD (Box-folder 002:013)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Emotional Communication and Countertransference in the Narcissistic and Borderline Disorder", 1977-78, TD (Box-folder 002:014)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Cat People - Between Reality and Fantasy", 1978, TD (Box-folder 002:015)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transsexualism and a New Type of Psychosurgery", 1978, TD (Box-folder 002:016)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Treatment of Established Pathological Mourners", 1980, TD (Box-folder 002:017)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transsexualism: As Examined From the Viewpoint of Internalized Object Relations", 1980, TD (Box-folder 002:018)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Reivew: Judd Marmor's Book, [Homosexual Behavior: A Modern Reappraisal], 1980, TD (Box-folder 002:019)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Review: Robert Langs and Harold Searles' Book, [Intrapsychic and Interpersonal Dimensions of Treament], 1980, TD (Box-folder 002:020)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transsexualism: As Examined from the Viewpoint of Internalized Object Relations" in On Sexuality: Psychoanalytic Observations1980, TD (Box-folder 002:021)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Review: Leonard L. and Renate Heston's Book, [The Medical Casebook of Adolf Hitler], 1980, TD (Box-folder 002:022)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Narcissistic Personality Organization 'Reparative' Leadership", 1980(4), TD (Box-folder 002:023)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Symposium: Commentary on Lloyd deMause's 'Historical Group Fantasies'", 1980(Fall), TD (Box-folder 002:024)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transference and Countertransference: An Examination from the Point of view of Internalized Object Relations", 1981, TD (Box-folder 002:025)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Students' Views on Death and Grieving" 1981, TD (Box-folder 002:026)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Narcissistic Personality Disorder" 1982, TD (Box-folder 002:027)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Young Woman's Disability to Say No to Needy People and Her Identification with the Frustrator in the Analytic Situation" 1982, TD (Box-folder 002:028)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Identification and Related Psychic Events: Their Appearance in Theory and Their Curative Value", 1982, TD (Box-folder 002:029)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Complicated Mourning and the Syndrome of Established Pathological Mourning", 1983, TD (Box-folder 002:030)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Complicated Mourning", 1984/5, TD (Box-folder 002:031)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Suitable Targets of Externalization and Schizophrenia", 1985, TD (Box-folder 002:032)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Review: William N. Confer and Billies S. Ables' Book, [Multiple Personality: Etiology, Diagnosis and Treatment], 1985, TD (Box-folder 002:033)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Need to Have Enemies and Allies: A Developmental Approach", 1985, TD (Box-folder 002:034)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Becoming an Psychoanalysist", 1985, TD (Box-folder 002:038)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Narcissism of Minor Differences in the Psychilogical Gap Between Opposing Nations", 1986, TD (Box-folder 003:001)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Six Constellations of Psychoanalytic Psychotheraphy of Borderline Patients" 1987, TD (Box-folder 003:002)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Development of Female Transsexualism", 1989, TD (Box-folder 003:003)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Turkish Fathers and Their Families: A Study on the Fathers and their Families in a Transitional Society", 1989, TD (Box-folder 003:004)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Psychoanalytic Psychotheraphy of Schizophrenia", 1989, TD (Box-folder 003:005)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Modified Psychoanalytic Technique for the Treatment of Borderline Patients" (German), 1990, TD (Box-folder 003:006)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Change, Mourning and Reorganization in Moscow", 1990, TD (Box-folder 003:007)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Lithuanians in Finland", 1990, TD (Box-folder 003:008)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Question of Germany: A West German's Reponse", 1990, TD (Box-folder 003:009)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Duelo Complicado" 1990, TD (Box-folder 003:010)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychological Processes in Unofficial Diplomacy Meetings", 1990, TD (Box-folder 003:011)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Prejudice As A Cultural / Political Phenomenon", 1990(10), TD (Box-folder 003:012)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Response to Critics of a Psychobiography", 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:013)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "An Interview with Valentian Berezhkov: Stalin's Interpreter", 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:014)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "On Chosen Trauma" 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:015)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Dilemma of Moscow: To Chage or Not to Change" 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:016)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Impact of Political Psychology on East-West Relationships: A Comment on President Ozal's Turkey in Europe, Europe in Turkey" 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:017)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Etiology of Schizophrenia and the Schizophrenic's Inner world", 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:018)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Why War - Revisited", 1991, TD (Box-folder 003:019)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: in "Psikiyatri Bulteni," Vol 1, No. 1 (Psychiatric Bulletin): "People Who Cannot Live without Cats: A Psychoanalytic Explanation" (Turkish), 1992, TD (Box-folder 003:020)
- "Die Bedeutung des Holocaust fur nicht direkt Betroffene" by Rafael Moses and Friedrich-Wilhelm Eickhoff (Book title: "Study of the Holocaust for Those Who Are Not Directly Involved In It"; "Volkans' Paper: What Does the Holocaust Mean to a Non-Jewish Psychoanalyst", 1992, TD (Box-folder 003:021)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Ethnonationalistic Rituals: An Introduction", 1992, TD (Box-folder 003:022)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Negotiating a Peaceful Separation: A Psychopolitical Analysis of Current Relationships Between Russia and the Baltic Republics", 1992, TD (Box-folder 003:023)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Inner World of the Schizophrenic Patient", 1992, TD (Box-folder 003:024)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Object-Relations Theory and Psychosomatic Illness", 1992(3), TD (Box-folder 003:025)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Object Relations Concept and Psychosomatic Illnesses" (Turkish) in Turkish Book "Scientific papers from the first psychosomatic symposium, March 12-14, 1992, Antalya, Turkey, 1992(3), TD (Box-folder 003:026)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper in "Korunk" journal: "Cyprus - War and Adaptation" (Romanian), 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:027)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper in "Korunk" journal: "Ethnic Identity - Psychodynamics of Ethnic Terrorism" (Romanian), 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:028)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Intrapsychic Story of Integration in a Borderline Patient", 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:029)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Countertransference Reactions Commonly Present in the Treatment of Patients with Boderline Personality organization", 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:030)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Immigrants and Refugees: A Psychodynamic Perspective", 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:031)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Istanbul, Not Constantinople: The Western World's View of 'the Turk'" 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:032)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Vaccinating the Political Process: A Second Psychopolitical Analysis of Relationships Between Russia and the Baltic States", 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:033)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "What the Holocaust Means to a Non-Jewish Psychoanalyst", 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:034)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Shaking the Tent: The Psychodynamics of Ethnic Terrorism", 1993, TD (Box-folder 003:035)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Identification with the Therapist's Functions and Ego Building in the Treatment of Schizophrenia" 1994, TD (Box-folder 003:036)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Treatment of Established Pathological Mourners", 1994, TD (Box-folder 003:037)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Discussion of 'the Borderline Personality Disorder' As a Sequel to Trauma", 1994(3), TD (Box-folder 004:001)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Totemism and Taboo in Romania: A Psycholotical Diagnosis", 1995, TD (Box-folder 004:002)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Uber die Notwendigkeit, Feinde und Verbundete zu haben (On the Necessity of Having Enemies and Allies)," German, but also have in English, published as a special issue of the journal "Die Zukunft Der Psychoanalyse" edited by Wilhelm Burian, 1995, TD (Box-folder 004:003)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Psychology of the Western European Neo-Racism", 1995, TD (Box-folder 004:004)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Psychodynamics of Ethnic Terrorism", 1995, TD (Box-folder 004:005)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Bosnia-Herzegovina: Ancient Fuel of a Modern Inferno", 1996, TD (Box-folder 004:006)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Review: S. Kakar's Book, [The Colors of Violence: Cultural Identities, Religion and Conflict], 1996, TD (Box-folder 004:007)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Tree Model: Psychopolitical Dialogues and the Promotion of Coexistence" 1997, TD (Box-folder 004:008)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Methological For Integrating Information in a Psuchoanalytic Biography" 1997, TD (Box-folder 004:009)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Foreword to 'Even Paranoids have Enemies'" 1998, TD (Box-folder 004:010)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Ethnicity and Nationalism: A Psychoanalytic Perspective", 1998, TD (Box-folder 004:011)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Psychoanalytic Perspective on Intergroup Hatred", 1998(Spring), TD (Box-folder 004:012)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "When Enemies Talk: Psychoanalytic Insight from Arab-Israel Dialogues" 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:013)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Individual and Large-Group Identity: Parallels in Development and Characteristics in Stability and Crisis" 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:014)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Nostalgia A a Linking Phenomenon", 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:015)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Tree Model: A Comprehensive Psychopolitical Approach to Un-official Diplomacy and the Reduction of Ethnic Tension", 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:016)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychoanalysis and Diplomacy Part I: Individual and Large Group Identity", 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:017)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychoanalysis and Diplomacy Part II: Large Group Rituals", 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:018)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychoanalysis and Diplomacy Part III: Potentials for and Obstacles against Collaboration", 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:019)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Claustrophobia Arising from Unconscious Womb Fantasies" 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:020)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Post-Traumatic States: Beyond Individual PTSD in Societies Ravaged by Ethinic Conflict", 1999, TD (Box-folder 004:021)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Layers Upon Layers: Politics, Psychology and Language in a Changing World" 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:022)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A View for Policy Makers: Interactive Conflict Resolution", 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:023)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Borderline-Psychopathologie und Internationale Beziehungen", 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:024)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Traumatized Societies and Psychological Care: Expending the Concept of Preventive Medicine", 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:025)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Borderline Psychopathology and International Relations," German, Book: "Handbook of Borderline Personality", 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:026)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Large-group Identity and Chosen Trauma," German, in "Psyche," German psychoanalytic journal, 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:027)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "A Psychololitical Approach foe the Reduction of Ethnic or Other Large-Group Regression", 2000, TD (Box-folder 004:028)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transgenerational Transmissions and Chosen Traumas: An Aspect of Large Group Identity", 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:029)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Anatomy of the Preparation for the Symposium, 'The End of Speechlessness'" German, 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:030)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Book Chapter: "Massive Trauma and Its Consequences," Dutch, in the book "Over een grens: Psychotherapie met adolescenten" (Across the Boundary: Psychotherapy with Adolescents), 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:031)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Diagnosis Before Action" 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:032)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychoanalysis and Diplomacy: Potentials for and Obstacles against Collaboration" 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:033)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Obervations on Religious Fundamentalism and the Taliban", 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:034)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Suicide Bombers", 2001, TD (Box-folder 004:035)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Foreword to 'Forensic Psychotheraphy and Psychopathology: Winnicottian Perspectives'" 2001, TD (Box-folder 005:001)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Enemy Images: Minor Differences and Dehumanizaion" in Serbian book "Psychoanalysis and War", 2001, TD (Box-folder 005:002)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Bosnia-Herzegovina: Chosen Trauma and Its Tansgenerationla Transmission", 2001(12), TD (Box-folder 005:003)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "September 11 and Societal Regression", 2002, TD (Box-folder 005:004)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Forward: Identity Issue - Migration and Persecution," German, Book is "Migration und Verfolgung: Psychoanalytische Perspektiven" (Migration and Persecution: Psycholanalytic Perspectives), 2002, TD (Box-folder 005:005)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Re-Libidinalization of the Internal World of a Refugee Family", 2003, TD (Box-folder 005:006)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Psychoanalyse in Internationalen Beziehungen und Internationale Beziehungenin der Psychoanalyse", 2004(12), TD (Box-folder 005:007)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Not Letting Go: From Individual Perennail Mourners to Societies with Entitlement Ideologies", 2006(6), TD (Box-folder 005:008)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "The Next Chapter: Consequences of Societal Trauma" 2006(11), TD (Box-folder 005:009)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Transgenerational Transmission and Deposited Representatations: Psychological Burdens Visited by One Generation Upon Another", 2007(5), TD (Box-folder 005:010)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Religious Fundamentalism and Violence", 2007, TD (Box-folder 005:011)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Introductory Remarks: Globalization, Otherness, and Psychoanalysis", 2008(3), TD (Box-folder 005:012)
- Vamik D.Volkan's Paper: "Large-Group Identity, International Relations and Psychoanalysis", 2008, TD (Box-folder 005:013)